Guide to the William R. Burt Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
William R. Burt papers
1940-1943
MS 1654
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.25
(1 box)
The papers consist of copies of charts and memoranda prepared by the War Department. The documents relate to the availability and condition of aircraft, their allocation to various theaters of operation, and efficient utilization of air power during World War II.
Burt, William R.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of William R. Burt, 1994.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The William R. Burt Papers consist of copies of charts and memoranda prepared by the War Department relating to the availability and condition of aircraft and their allocation to the various theaters of operation to efficiently utilize air power during World War II. The collection was the gift of William R. Burt in 1994.
Biographical / Historical
William R. Burt served as staff officer to General Hoyt S. Vandenberg during 1940-1946, as well as Secretary of Air Staff for the USAAF in Washington, D.C. He also served as duty officer for the Allied Expeditionary Air Force and as Chief of Policy and Liaison for Air Division U.S. Control Council, Berlin.
Air power; Air warfare; World War, 1939-1945 -- Aerial operations, American; Burt, William R.
- Inventory
  - "Materiel Division's Estimate of Deliveries of Airplanes", 1941 July - August (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Report on Condition of Combat Airplanes (in Accordance with CTI-309)" (with cover letter), 1941 July - December (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Actual airplane acceptances classified by customer and type (by months 1941)", 1941 August - November (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Allocation of Airplanes: 16 groups - 1st aviation strength, 1941 September (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Allocation of Airplanes: 54 group program - 1st aviation objective and the augmentation of these groups to 2nd aviation strength, 1941 September - November (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Graphs (by month, geographical location, divisions)"- Heavy Bombers- Medium Bombers- Light Bombers- Pursuit Group Allotments, [ 1941 ] (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Airplane Allocation (25 Group Program)"- Bombardment-heavy- Bombardment-light and medium- Pursuit- Observation- Transports, 1940 October (Box 1, Folder 2 - 3)
  - "Preference List as a Guide in Making Allocations," memo for Joint Aircraft Committee from Special Committee on Revision of Preference List (Exhibit C), 1941 Sept, October (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "Report of Number of Airplanes that can be Maintained in Combat", 1941 November (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "Recapitulation of Air Corps Units", [ 1941 ] (Box 1, Folder 3)